<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>MeshCMS User Guide</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <title>MeshCMS User Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Luciano</firstname>

      <surname>Vernaschi</surname>
    </author>

    <abstract>
      <para>MeshCMS is a simple content management system written in Java.
      This guide illustrates the most common operations that MeshCMS users
      will need to learn, from installation to daily usage.</para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>MeshCMS is an online editing system written in Java. It provides a
    set of features usually included in a CMS, but it uses a more traditional
    approach: pages are stored in regular HTML files and all additional
    features are file-based.</para>

    <para>MeshCMS is available under the <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GPL license</ulink>. It allows
    some different usage approaches:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>it can be used as a simple, basic CMS. The user interface allows
        to edit pages visually, add and delete pages and do other basic tasks.
        This kind of approach should be easy enough for everyone;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>more experienced users can create complex themes and modules to
        fulfill specific needs. MeshCMS offers many convenience classes and
        methods, and it allows to create JSP pages that will be added to the
        site map just like plain HTML pages;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>since MeshCMS uses plain files and supports the usual SiteMesh
        configuration, many external Java applications can be integrated quite
        easily.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Main features are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">file-based</emphasis> - no database
        needed;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">easy to install</emphasis> - deploy
        meshcms.war and you're done (tested on Tomcat and Jetty);</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">multi-site support</emphasis> - multiple
        sites can be served with a single installation on a single
        context;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">compatible with other editors</emphasis> -
        since it is file-based, you can edit your files with other programs if
        you want, then upload them as usual;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">cross-browser</emphasis> - tested with
        Internet Explorer and Firefox;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">wysiwyg editor included</emphasis> - uses
        <ulink url="http://tinymce.moxiecode.com/">TinyMCE</ulink>;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">file manager</emphasis> with image
        thumbnails, file operations, clipboard, upload, download, unzip and
        other functions - can also be used from within the wysiwyg editor to
        select links and images;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>support for <emphasis role="bold">themes</emphasis> - uses
        <ulink url="http://www.opensymphony.com/sitemesh/">SiteMesh</ulink> as
        engine;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>support for <emphasis role="bold">modules</emphasis> to create
        commonly used components automatically - some module templates are
        provided (image gallery, mail form, download list, site map and
        others);</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">tag library</emphasis> to create new
        themes easily - menus and other common components are created
        automatically;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>optional <emphasis role="bold">hotlinking prevention</emphasis>
        - inspired by <ulink
        url="http://www.alistapart.com/articles/hotlinking/">this
        article</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="install">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <section id="install_basic">
      <title>Basic Procedures</title>

      <para>If you want to try MeshCMS, the simplest way to get started is to
      copy meshcms.war into the webapps folder of your application server
      (e.g. <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/">Tomcat</ulink> or
      <ulink url="http://jetty.mortbay.org/">Jetty</ulink>) and open
      <emphasis>http://localhost:8080/meshcms/</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>If you want to deploy a website, you will have to configure a
      virtual host for it as usual. There is nothing special in the setup of
      MeshCMS, so please refer to the documentation of your application server
      to choose the configuration options that best suit your needs.</para>

      <para>MeshCMS is able to create thumbnails of images, so you need to
      provide an environment that allows image processing. On some systems you
      might need to add the <option>-Djava.awt.headless=true</option> option
      to the Java VM that runs the Servlet container.</para>

      <para>Starting from version 3.0, MeshCMS allows to serve multiple sites
      from within a single context. If you want to do this, you should
      configure the context to accept all domains that you want to host.
      Here's a simple example of <filename>server.xml</filename> file for
      Tomcat 5.5 that accepts all domain names:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;Server port="8005" shutdown="SHUTDOWN"&gt;
  &lt;Service name="Catalina"&gt;
    &lt;Connector port="8080" /&gt;

    &lt;Engine name="Catalina" defaultHost="localhost"&gt;
      &lt;Host name="localhost" appBase="/home/tomcat"&gt;
        &lt;Context path="" docBase="/meshcms" debug="0" reloadable="false" allowLinking="false" /&gt;
      &lt;/Host&gt;
    &lt;/Engine&gt;
  &lt;/Service&gt;
&lt;/Server&gt;</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section id="upgrade">
      <title>Upgrade</title>

      <para>MeshCMS is composed of two folders:
      <filename>/meshcms/admin</filename> and <filename>/WEB-INF</filename>.
      To perform an upgrade, you should delete the current versions of those
      folders and use the new ones. Be careful not to delete the whole
      <filename>/meshcms</filename> folder, but just the
      <filename>admin</filename> subfolder.</para>

      <para>This upgrade strategy works fine in case of a simple usage of
      MeshCMS. In other cases the upgrade process can be harder. You probably
      won't modify the contents of the <filename>/meshcms/admin</filename>
      folder, but the <filename>/WEB-INF</filename> one is more likely to be
      changed. If you want to add an external application, or if you want to
      configure SiteMesh differently, you must keep track of your changes so
      that you can integrate them with the new release.</para>

      <para>Upgrading from version prior to 3.0 is even harder. While the HTML
      files created before will continue to work fine (module contents
      included), there's no tool in the official release to convert users and
      site configurations. Such tools might become available on the community
      website. Furthermore, some files (for example themes and modules) need
      to be renamed and moved manually to match the new file structure.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="basic_concepts">
    <title>Basic Concepts</title>

    <section id="site_map">
      <title>The Site Map</title>

      <para>The site map is one of the most important MeshCMS components.
      Since MeshCMS is file based, there is no site map defined in a database,
      so MeshCMS must figure it out by parsing the file system. The site map
      is not a simple list of pages: it is a hierarchical structure which
      follows some strict rules.</para>

      <para>The key of the site map is the concept of <firstterm>welcome
      file</firstterm>. This concept is well known by webmasters. When you
      access <uri>http://www.site.com/somefolder/somepage.html</uri>, the file
      <filename>somepage.html</filename> located in the
      <filename>/somedir</filename> folder is sent to your browser. But when
      you access <uri>http://www.site.com/somefolder/</uri>, you are
      requesting a folder, not a file. In such case, a file with a specific
      name is searched into that folder and, if it is available, that file is
      sent to your browser. Usually this file is called
      <filename>index.html</filename>, but more than one can be specified, and
      the first match will be used. The default for MeshCMS is to search for
      <filename>index.html</filename>, then <filename>index.htm</filename> and
      finally <filename>index.jsp</filename> (you can change this by editing
      the <filename>web.xml</filename> configuration file according to the
      Servlet specification). The result of this convention is that accessing
      <uri>http://www.site.com/somefolder/</uri> and accessing
      <uri>http://www.site.com/somefolder/index.html</uri> will lead to the
      same page.</para>

      <para>MeshCMS uses the welcome files heavily. When it encounters a
      folder while parsing the website tree, it checks whether that folder
      contains a welcome file or not. If there is no welcome file, <emphasis
      role="bold">that folder is ignored</emphasis>, along with all
      subfolders. This means that all pages included in that folder will
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> be included in the site map, and that users
      will not find those pages in the navigation menu.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Pages included in ignored folders are still available by using a
        direct link or by typing the full address in the browser location
        bar.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Why is the site map made this way? There are two main reasons. The
      first one is that if a folder without welcome file were included in the
      navigation menu, clicking on it would show a listing of the folder
      contents, or an error page if that listing is not allowed. So this is a
      way to force the use of a welcome page. The second reason is that there
      are many cases where a page must not be available in the navigation
      menu. Suppose that you want to use the <link linkend="modules">include
      module template</link> to add some news in your web pages. You will
      create a folder that will contain an HTML file for each news, and then
      you will use that folder as module argument. If none of the HTML files
      has the name of a welcome file, those news will not be inserted in the
      navigation menu directly, but they will still available for the module
      as expected. This is just an example of a situation in which a welcome
      file should not be used.</para>

      <para>When a folder contains a welcome file, it is inserted in the site
      map, and all other items available in that folder are included as
      children pages. Items can be files (HTML or server-side pages) or
      folders (which must have their own welcome file as explained
      above).</para>

      <para>This method has an important drawback: <emphasis role="bold">a
      page that is not a welcome file cannot have children pages</emphasis>.
      For example, there is no way to add a child page to
      <uri>http://www.site.com/somefolder/somepage.html</uri>. This is usually
      not a problem, since you can always create a page at the same level (for
      example <uri>http://www.site.com/somefolder/otherpage.html</uri>), but
      if you think you will want to add children pages to a page, use a new
      folder for it. Keep in mind that
      <uri>http://www.site.com/somefolder/somepage.html</uri> and
      <uri>http://www.site.com/somefolder/somepage/index.html</uri> are
      indexed <emphasis role="bold">exactly in the same way</emphasis>. If you
      create new pages using the <link linkend="manage_pages">Manage
      Pages</link> tool, leave the "Create enclosing folder" box checked, so
      you will be able to add children pages to your new page in
      future.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="external_tools">
      <title>External Documents and Tools</title>

      <para>One of the reasons that led to the creation of MeshCMS was the
      need to manage hundreds of HTML documents created previously, and to be
      able to add some Microsoft Word documents if needed. As a consequence,
      MehsCMS accepts any HTML file that it finds while exploring the website
      folder to create the site map. Thanks to the power of SiteMesh, pages
      created in different ways are parsed and decorated, while the title can
      be extracted to be used in the site menu.</para>

      <para>Some MeshCMS users constantly upload Word documents converted to
      HTML, while others edit pages directly on the web using external tools
      like Macromedia Contribute, which they can find more comfortable than
      using the online editor provided by MeshCMS.</para>

      <para>This approach has led to some choices that are different from the
      ones made for other CMSes. For example, there's no need to specify in
      which order pages must be inserted in the navigation menu. While one can
      prefer to take full control of that order, this is really tedious when
      dealing with hundreds of documents. MeshCMS automatically puts the
      welcome file at the beginning on the list and then orders the other
      pages according to the number of visits in the last days. This brings
      the most interesting documents at the beginning of the list.</para>

      <para>The <link linkend="manage_pages">Manage Pages</link> tool offers
      an option to assign a <firstterm>score</firstterm> to each page. Pages
      with higher score will always come first, regardless of the count of
      visits. It is a tedious process to use scores to order the whole site
      map, and it is not a user-friendly method at all. But partial orderings
      are allowed: default score is zero for all pages, so one can assign a
      score just to those pages that he wants to see at the beginning
      (positive score) or at the end (negative score) of the list. Pages with
      the same score are ordered according to the number of visits.</para>

      <para>Most users assign a score to first-level pages (for example: home
      page, company profile, products and finally contacts), while subpages
      are left without score.</para>

      <para>Another consequence of the need to support documents that come
      from many sources is that MeshCMS does not check them for standard
      compliance. It respects the generalistic approach that is allowed by
      SiteMesh. Of course, a web developer is still allowed to put all
      document type definitions in his own themes and to require his users to
      deal with well-formed documents only.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="multiple_sites">
      <title>Serving multiple sites from a single installation</title>

      <para>Tomcat and other servlet containers allow to create multiple
      hosts, and to put multiple contexts within them. Web developers usually
      need to host more than a single website on the same server, so they end
      up creating a host for each website and specifying which domains must be
      served by that host. This is a good setup strategy since it allows to
      separate sites and to tune their configuration. Nevertheless, this
      method leads to many installations of MeshCMS that must be maintained
      separately, which is quite annoying, for example when upgrading.</para>

      <para>MeshCMS 3.0 gives the choice between this approach and a different
      one: you can install it once and serve all sites from that single
      context. You will probably configure the host to serve all domains and
      let MeshCMS map them to different sites. The advantages of this approach
      are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>you have to deal with a single installation of the
          software;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>you will save some server resources;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>you can see the files of all sites from the file manager if
          you have the needed permissions;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>you can configure the sites and their mappings using the web
          interface.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The drawbacks are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>it is more difficult to manage security separately for each
          site;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>if you use JSP pages in virtual sites, you must keep into
          account the fact that MeshCMS will map URLs to files
          differently.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To serve multiple sites, you need to install MeshCMS as usual.
      Then you can use the <link linkend="control_panel">Control Panel</link>
      to create new sites.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Main site and virtual sites</title>

        <para>When you install MeshCMS, you have a single site. This is the
        good old default scenario. You can add a virtually unlimited number of
        virtual sites on top of it. While virtual sites behave like the main
        one apparently, there are some differences between. The main
        difference is the fact that a different file is served when a page of
        a virtual site is requested. Normally, if you configure a Tomcat host
        to serve <uri>www.site1.com</uri> and <uri>www.site2.com</uri>, the
        same file will be served for
        <uri>http://www.site1.com/index.html</uri> and
        <uri>http://www.site2.com/index.html</uri>. That file is simply
        <filename>/index.html</filename>, located in the root context. But if
        you setup <uri>www.site2.com</uri> as a virtual site on top of
        <uri>www.site1.com</uri>, a request for
        <uri>http://www.site2.com/index.html</uri> will lead to
        <filename>/meshcms/sites/site2.com/index.html</filename>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="common_tasks">
    <title>Common Tasks</title>

    <section id="create_theme">
      <title>Create a Theme</title>

      <para>One of the essential features of a CMS is the ability to apply a
      common look &amp; feel to many pages, adding the graphics and some other
      components like the navigation menu. In MeshCMS you can achieve this
      result by using a <firstterm>theme</firstterm>. There is a special
      folder in MeshCMS whose default path is <filename>/themes</filename>
      (you can change that path in the <link
      linkend="configure">Configuration</link>). A theme is a subfolder of
      <filename>/themes</filename> that contains all the elements needed by
      the theme itself. Those elements are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the theme main file: a JSP page named
          <filename>main.jsp</filename> that defines the common part of the
          pages and where the variable parts must be inserted;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the theme CSS: a CSS file named <filename>main.css</filename>
          that has the only special feature of being automatically linked from
          the page if the <link
          linkend="tag_defaultcss">&lt;cms:defaultcss&gt;</link> custom tag is
          used. This should always be done, since using that syntax, the CSS
          will also be sent to the wysiwyg editor to display the page body
          being edited;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>an additional CSS for MeshCMS specific styles (mail forms and
          page editor), named <filename>meshcms.css</filename>. If this CSS is
          not found in the theme, the default one will be used. You can
          override it if you want to change the appearance of those two
          components (the default is located in the
          <filename>/admin/theme</filename> folder);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>any other file needed by the theme: other CSS files, images,
          javascripts and so on. You can then use these files in your main
          file by inserting the <link
          linkend="tag_themepath">&lt;cms:themepath&gt;</link> tag that will
          be replaced with the right path to the theme folder.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>You can assign a theme to a page using the <link
      linkend="manage_pages">Manage Pages</link> tool in the Control Panel.
      There's no need to assign a theme to each page: if a page has no theme,
      the theme of the parent will be used. For example, if
      <uri>www.yoursite.com/apage.html</uri> has no theme, it will look like
      <uri>www.yoursite.com</uri>. In many cases a theme is assigned to the
      home page and that's all.</para>

      <section id="theme_main_file">
        <title>The Theme Main File</title>

        <para>The main file of a theme is a JSP file that will include
        component of the page being shown:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;%@ taglib uri="meshcms-taglib" prefix="cms" %&gt;

&lt;html&gt;
 &lt;head&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;&lt;cms:pagetitle /&gt;&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;cms:defaultcss /&gt;
  &lt;cms:pagehead /&gt;
 &lt;/head&gt;

 &lt;body&gt;
  &lt;cms:editor&gt;
   &lt;cms:pagebody /&gt;
  &lt;/cms:editor&gt;
 &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This theme file is very basic, but it works: when applied to the
        sample MeshCMS home page, it looks this way:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>The simplest theme ever with a minimal CSS file (just to
          show that it works too)</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="bare_viewing.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The same basic theme can be used to edit the page:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>The simplest theme used to edit the same
          page</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="bare_editing.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Now you know that a basic theme isn't complicated at all. In
        fact, it is a normal HTML page (which you can create with your
        favorite editor), that includes some <link
        linkend="tag_library">custom tags</link> that will be replaced by
        MeshCMS with the contents of the page. This is how MeshCMS translates
        the page above:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;html&gt;
 &lt;head&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Home Page&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;link type="text/css" rel="stylesheet" href="/meshcms/themes/bare/main.css" /&gt;
  &lt;link type="text/css" rel="stylesheet" href="/meshcms/admin/theme/meshcms.css" /&gt;
  &lt;meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8"&gt;
 &lt;/head&gt;

 &lt;body&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Welcome to MeshCMS 2.0. Here is a list ...&lt;/p&gt;
  ...
 &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>When you create a theme, you should create a normal HTML page
        along with its own CSS file and images and store all files in a folder
        (you can use subfolders if you want). Use some text placeholder to
        point out where to put page components. For example, write [TITLE]
        where you expect to see the title of the page, [SITE MENU] where you
        want to see the menu, [BODY] where the text of the page should be
        located and so on. Please note that the notation with square brackets
        has nothing special. They are just placeholders. You might also use
        the "lorem ipsum" text instead of [BODY]. Your file might look like
        this one:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>A skeleton for a theme file</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="theme_step1.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>This is the corresponding HTML code:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;[TITLE]&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body style="margin: 0px;"&gt;
&lt;table width="770" border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0"&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td colspan="2" valign="bottom"
      style="background: url(flowers.jpg) no-repeat; height: 120px; padding: 10px; font-size: 22px;"&gt;[TITLE]&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td bgcolor="#E2E0C9"&gt;&lt;table border="0" align="center" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0"&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Site Menu:&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[SITE MENU]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;MeshCMS Menu:&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[MESHCMS MENU]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="5"&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[BREADCRUMBS]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[BODY]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr align="center"&gt;
    &lt;td colspan="2" bgcolor="#DDBC00"&gt;
      Powered by &lt;a href="http://www.cromoteca.com/meshcms/"&gt;MeshCMS&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;

&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>When you are happy with your page, open it with a source code
        editor. Replace:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[TITLE] with <code>&lt;cms:pagetitle /&gt;</code></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[SITE MENU] with <code>&lt;cms:simplemenu
            /&gt;</code></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[MESHCMS MENU] with <code>&lt;cms:adminmenu
            /&gt;</code></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[BREADCRUMBS] with <code>&lt;cms:breadcrumbs
            /&gt;</code></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[BODY] with <code>&lt;cms:pagebody /&gt;</code></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>There is a link to an image in the file: you must add
        <code>&lt;cms:themepath /&gt;</code> before the image path so it will
        be found correctly. <code>url(flowers.jpg)</code> becomes
        <code>url(&lt;cms:themepath /&gt;/flowers.jpg)</code>.</para>

        <para>Then add this line at the beginning of your file:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;%@ taglib uri="meshcms-taglib" prefix="cms" %&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>Save your file and name it <filename>main.jsp</filename>. The
        CSS must be named <filename>main.css</filename> and must be located in
        the same folder. This folder must be located in the
        <filename>/themes</filename> folder in your site (this location can be
        changed in the <link linkend="configure">Configuration</link>), and
        the name of the folder will be used as name of the theme itself. All
        images and other files must be located in the same folder. You can use
        subfolders, but then you need to write paths accordingly: for example,
        if you put all images in a subfolder called
        <filename>images</filename>, you will use <code>url(&lt;cms:themepath
        /&gt;/images/flowers.jpg)</code> in the example above.</para>

        <para>When your brand new decorator is available, reopen the home page
        of your web site and your new look &amp; feel should now be used to
        display the page:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>The new theme in use</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="theme_step2.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">&lt;%@ taglib uri="meshcms-taglib" prefix="cms" %&gt;</emphasis>

&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;<emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:pagetitle /&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body style="margin: 0px;"&gt;
&lt;table width="770" border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0"&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td colspan="2" valign="bottom"
      style="background: url(<emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:themepath /&gt;</emphasis>/flowers.jpg) no-repeat; height: 120px; padding: 10px; font-size: 22px;"&gt;<emphasis
            role="bold">&lt;cms:pagetitle /&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td bgcolor="#E2E0C9"&gt;&lt;table border="0" align="center" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0"&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Site Menu:&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;<emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:simplemenu /&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;MeshCMS Menu:&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;<emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:adminmenu separator="&lt;br /&gt;" /&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="5"&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;<emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:breadcrumbs /&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;<emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:pagebody /&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr align="center"&gt;
    &lt;td colspan="2" bgcolor="#DDBC00"&gt;
      Powered by &lt;a href="http://www.cromoteca.com/meshcms/"&gt;MeshCMS&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;

&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>There are other tags that you must add in your decorator:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>&lt;cms:pagehead /&gt;</code> and
            <code>&lt;cms:defaultcss /&gt;</code> go inside the
            <code>&lt;head&gt;</code> tag of your file to include headers and
            CSS;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>&lt;cms:editor&gt;...&lt;/cms:editor&gt;</code> must
            enclose all the contents of the <code>&lt;body&gt;</code>
            tag;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>&lt;cms:setlocale /&gt;</code> to define the locale of
            the pages that will use the theme;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>you will probably want to add one or more <link
            linkend="modules">modules</link>;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>other <link linkend="tag_library">tags</link> could be
            useful in some cases.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>After these other modifications, you should get this source
        code:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;%@ taglib uri="meshcms-taglib" prefix="cms" %&gt;
<emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:setlocale value="en" /&gt;</emphasis>

&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;
    &lt;cms:pagetitle /&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:pagehead /&gt;</emphasis>
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:defaultcss /&gt;</emphasis>
  &lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body style="margin: 0px;"&gt;<emphasis role="bold">&lt;cms:editor&gt;</emphasis>
&lt;table width="770" border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0"&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td colspan="2" valign="bottom"
      style="background: url(&lt;cms:themepath /&gt;/flowers.jpg) no-repeat; height: 120px; padding: 10px; font-size: 22px;"&gt;&lt;cms:pagetitle /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td bgcolor="#E2E0C9"&gt;&lt;table border="0" align="center" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0"&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Site Menu:&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;cms:simplemenu /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;MeshCMS Menu:&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;cms:adminmenu separator="&lt;br /&gt;" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="5"&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;cms:breadcrumbs /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;cms:pagebody /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr align="center"&gt;
    &lt;td colspan="2" bgcolor="#DDBC00"&gt;
      Powered by &lt;a href="http://www.cromoteca.com/meshcms/"&gt;MeshCMS&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
<emphasis role="bold">&lt;/cms:editor&gt;</emphasis>&lt;/body&gt;

&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="create_mail_form">
      <title>Create a Mail Form</title>

      <para>The WYSIWYG editor does not allow to create mail forms. To fill
      this gap, MeshCMS provides two ways to add a mail form to a page. In
      both cases, messages sent through that form will be delivered to an
      address you specify (which will not be visible to anyone, since it's not
      displayed in the page and not included in its source code).</para>

      <para>The two methods are:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>you can specify an e-mail address in the "E-mail for comments"
          field while editing a page. A simple form will be inserted into the
          page and the address you entered will receive the messages. The form
          can't be customized, but this method is very easy to apply and will
          be enough for most situations. To be able to use this method, the
          page theme must contain the <code>&lt;cms:mailform&gt;</code>
          tag;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>a module is available that parses a text file and builds a
          form based on simple instructions. This method offers more options
          and will be described in the rest of this page, since it requires to
          learn the syntax to be used in the text file. To be able to use this
          method, the page theme must contain at least one configurable
          <code>&lt;cms:module&gt;</code> tag.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>To create a form using the second method, you must write a text
      file following a specific syntax. As a first example, let's create the
      simplest form you could use (similar to the one provided by the first
      method):</para>

      <programlisting>recipient:name@site.com

Name

E-mail
email
sender

Message
text:12

Send
submit</programlisting>

      <para>Field definition blocks are separated by empty lines. The first
      line of each block indicates the field name. Let's look at each block
      separately:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the first line specifies the <option>recipient</option>
          address;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>"Name" is a text field. This is the default when no other
          parameters are specified;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>"E-mail" is a text field that is expected to contain an
          <option>e-mail</option> address (a check will be executed to verify
          this condition). Its value will be used as <option>sender</option>
          address;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>"Message" and is a text area of <option>12</option>
          rows;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the next element is a <option>submit</option> button whose
          label is "Send this message".</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Here's how to add a drop down box:</para>

      <programlisting>recipient:name@site.com

Name

E-mail
email
sender

<emphasis role="bold">Topic
options: Information, Support Request, Feedback</emphasis>

Message
text:16

Send Now
submit</programlisting>

      <para>Other notes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the default field type is <option>text</option>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the <option>number</option> field type can be used for fields
          that require a numeric value;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the <option>reset</option> field inserts a reset button. A
          label can be specified as for the <option>submit</option>
          button;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>buttons are inserted at the end of the form, regardless of the
          field order;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the <option>textarea</option> field type is a synonym of
          <option>text:12</option>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the <option>value</option>: line can be used for all fields of
          type <option>text</option>, <option>email</option>,
          <option>number</option> and <option>textarea</option> to provide a
          default value;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the <option>sendername</option> attribute indicates that the
          field value must be used as name of the sender;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the <option>subject</option> attribute indicates that the
          field value will be the subject of the message;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the <option>message</option> attribute will insert the field
          value "as is", i.e. without specifying the field name;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>you can't insert a new line while defining a parameter. Each
          parameter (field name, field type, options, etc.) goes on its own
          line.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>A more complex example is shown here:</para>

      <programlisting>recipient:name@site.com

Note
hidden
value: This is a hidden note

Name
sendername

E-mail
email
sender

Gender
options: male, female

Age
options: less than 13, 13-20, 21-30, 31-40, 41-50, 51-60, more than 60

Subject
subject
value: Hello
required

Message
text:16
required

Send Now
submit

Reset All Fields
reset</programlisting>

      <para>And here's how it looks in the browser:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Mail form</screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="sample_mail_form.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Finally, this is the default MeshCMS form in English (recipient is
      not specified since it is added in the page editor):</para>

      <programlisting>Name
sendername

E-mail
email
sender

Message
textarea
messagebody

Send Now
submit</programlisting>

      <para>Required fields are shown in bold by default. You can change this
      by creating a <filename>meshcms.css</filename> file in your
      theme.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="edit_page">
      <title>Edit a Page</title>

      <para>Once you have logged in, you should see some links to edit a page
      while viewing it. Select "Edit this page" and the wysiwyg editor (<ulink
      url="http://tinymce.moxiecode.com/">TinyMCE</ulink>) will show up, along
      with other fields to edit the page title and the various modules.</para>

      <para>Editing a page shouldn't be that hard. TinyMCE provides a standard
      interface to write text and format it as desired. It comes with its own
      help.</para>

      <para>MeshCMS adds the ability to browse for links and images. Just
      click on the <inlinegraphic fileref="browse_button.gif" /> Browse icon
      in the image and link popups to access the file manager with all its
      functions (upload included). The link popup also contains a drop down
      list with all pages available in the site map to insert links in a
      moment.</para>

      <note>
        <para>in some cases, when saving a page you might want to unckeck the
        "use relative URLs when saving" option, so local links will be saved
        with the full path. This is useful when saving pages to be included
        with the include <link linkend="modules">module</link>: this option
        will allow links included in that pages to work regardless of the page
        in which they will be included.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="create_new_page">
      <title>Create a New Page</title>

      <para>In MeshCMS a page is a file. Period. Having said that, there are
      three ways to add a new page:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>open the <link linkend="file_manager">File Manager</link> and
          create a new HTML file in the desired place. Please keep in mind how
          the <link linkend="site_map">site map</link> is created;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>(much easier) open the <link linkend="control_panel">Control
          Panel</link>, then choose <link linkend="manage_pages">Manage
          Pages</link>. Choose the <inlinegraphic
          fileref="newpage_button.gif" /> icon associated to the right page:
          you will add a child page to that one. A small popup will open.
          Insert a title for the page (use a short one since it wiil be used
          to choose a name for the file: you will be able to change it while
          editing the page). Uncheck <option>Create enclosing folder</option>
          only if you are absolutely sure that you won't add a child page to
          the new one in future. Then click on <command>Create</command> and
          the editor will be opened;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>(the easiest way) navigate to a page and click on <option>New
          page</option> or on <option>New child page</option>. You will add a
          new page at the same level of the current one or a child page
          respectively. Then continue as above (insert the title and so
          on).</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Additionally, you can add (and edit) pages from outside MeshCMS,
      for example using an FTP client. After doing that, make sure you run
      <command>Refresh Site Map</command> in the Control Panel so MeshCMS can
      find your new page(s).</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="control_panel">
    <title>Control Panel</title>

    <para>This is the home page of the MeshCMS admin area. It contains icons
    for the most operations. Icons are shown or hidden according to user's
    privileges.</para>

    <para>Some of them are very simple: there is a link to the home page, a
    button to log in or out and a button to refresh the site map. This one is
    useful when something has been changed from outside MeshCMS (e.g. via FTP
    or some shell), when you want to empty the cache for some reason, or when
    you want menus to be re-ordered according to current page hits.</para>

    <para>Other functions are more complex and are described in separate
    sections.</para>

    <section id="file_manager">
      <title>File Manager</title>

      <para>The MeshCMS file manager is a web-based version of the file
      manager you probably use daily on your computer. It allows to manage the
      file system of your website.</para>

      <para>The look &amp; feel of the file manager window should be familiar
      to everyone. On the left there is the folder tree, while the contents of
      the currently opened folder are shown on the right. There you can select
      some items and choose an action from the menu at the top of the
      window.</para>

      <para>Most of the menu items are easy to understand. Probably the
      <property>Themes</property> menu is the most <quote>obscure</quote>, in
      fact it is rarely used. This menu allows to specify what theme should be
      applied to a page or folder. Normally it's easier to apply themes using
      the <link linkend="manage_pages">Manage Pages</link> feature of the
      Control Panel, but using the file manager you can apply themes even to
      files not included in the site map. Simply select the desired items and
      then pick a theme for them. If you choose <option>Don't
      Specify</option>, the theme will be inherited from the parent folder
      (this is the default for all items that don't have an associated theme,
      in fact if you only select a theme for the home page, all other pages
      will use it). If you choose <option>No Theme</option>, nothing will be
      applied to that file, which will be shown "as is".</para>

      <section id="upload">
        <title>Upload</title>

        <para>The upload tool is essential, since it is used to add new files.
        You can upload one file at a time, so if you need to upload many
        files, you better create a ZIP archive, upload it and finally <link
        linkend="unzip">unzip</link> it.</para>

        <para>To upload a file, navigate to the desired folder and select
        <command>Upload</command> from the <option>Tools</option> menu. Then
        select the file from your computer and start uploading.</para>

        <important>
          <para>a file with the same name will be overwritten without
          confirmation.</para>
        </important>
      </section>

      <section id="unzip">
        <title>Unzip</title>

        <para>You can unpack a ZIP archive from within the file manager. It
        will be unpacked in the same folder or in a subfolder, so make sure to
        put it in the right place before unzipping (you can always move the
        unpacked items later).</para>

        <para>Select the ZIP file (it can have any extension) and choose
        <command>Unzip</command> from the <option>Tools</option> menu. You'll
        see a list of the files that are packed into the archive. If you
        prefer, you can check the flag to unzip the files in a new folder and
        edit its name. Note that many archives already put all files in a
        folder: you can verify if this is the case by looking at the list of
        files.</para>

        <important>
          <para>this operation is quite dangerous, since it will overwrite
          files if needed, without backing them up. So it is highly
          recommended to unzip files in a new folder as described
          above.</para>
        </important>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="manage_pages">
      <title>Manage Pages</title>

      <para>Here the site map is shown in a convenient way and some actions
      are available for each page. The table has these columns:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Page title</emphasis>: shows the title
          of the page, preceded by an icon that allows to show/hide children
          pages (if any).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Hits</emphasis>: a count of the page
          hits in the last days. This is not serious statistics, but since
          this count is stored to be used when sorting pages, it is shown here
          to have a rough idea of how much a page is being visited.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Cache</emphasis>: indicates if the page
          is currently available in the page cache.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Menu Caption</emphasis>: the name of the
          page in the navigation menus, breadcrumbs and links. If the field is
          empty, the page title will be used instead.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Theme</emphasis>: the theme used for the
          page. If the field is empty, the theme of the parent will be used.
          If <option>no theme</option> is selected, the page will be shown "as
          is".</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Score</emphasis>: a number that
          indicates the <quote>importance</quote> of the page. This value is
          used to sort pages in menus. Pages with the same score are sorted
          according to their hits. If the score is not specified, its value is
          zero, so you can use a negative value to put pages at the end of the
          list.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Actions</emphasis>: icons to create a
          new child page or delete a page. Not all pages can have children
          pages (see <xref linkend="site_map" /> to know why). Pages with
          children cannot be deleted, although you can always use the file
          manager to delete them anyway.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="edit_profile">
      <title>Edit Profile</title>

      <para>The purpose of this page is simple: you can change your password
      and edit your profile. Details are optional. The e-mail is optional too,
      but is located between the required elements since there's the plan to
      add a simple message board in future.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new_user">
      <title>New User</title>

      <para>To create a new user, you need to specify these info:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">username</emphasis>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">user type</emphasis>:
          <option>Administrator</option> has all privileges,
          <option>Editor</option> can edit pages but can't do admin stuff and
          <option>Member</option> can browse files and not much more (in fact
          it is rarely used);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">home folder</emphasis>: the folder in
          which the user can edit files;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">password</emphasis>: an initial password
          that can be changed later by the user himself.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>All other details are optional.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="configure">
      <title>Configure</title>

      <para>The configure page is available to administrators only. Editable
      options are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Visually editable types</emphasis>: a
          comma-separated list of file types that can be edited using the
          wysiwyg editor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Use system theme</emphasis>: if this
          option is selected, the default system theme will be used for the
          control panel and for all other administrative pages. While it is
          preferable to use the same theme as the rest of the site, it is
          recommended to turn this option on while editing themes, so admin
          pages are always available without errors.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Prevent hotlinking</emphasis>: if
          selected, others are not allowed to link to your images and files
          directly: they must link to pages on your site. A simple window will
          be shown to state that the file comes from your site.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">SMTP Server</emphasis>: the server used
          to send e-mail messages when a visitor compiles a mail form. You
          must specify its name; username and password are required only if
          the server uses SMTP authentication.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Page cache</emphasis>: used to activate
          the page caching. This is highly recommended since the "decoration"
          of a page is a quite expensive task. If you have much memory (or few
          pages), you can store cached pages in memory, otherwise save them on
          disk. Pages are saved in GZIP format and are sent compressed when
          the browser supports that (always true with modern browsers).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Site map update interval
          (hours)</emphasis>: the validity of the site map. After the
          specified amount of hours, the site map is recreated and the page
          cache is emptied.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Backup life (days)</emphasis>: the
          validity of backup files. Those files are stored in the repository.
          While there is no interface to manage them at the moment, they are
          still available in the file system so a deleted file can be
          recovered in case of mistake using an FTP client or some other
          shell.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Hits counting period (days)</emphasis>:
          page hits are counted for some days to allow to sort pages when no
          other criteria is available. If you change this value, the new one
          will be used after a restart of the web application.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Preferred charset</emphasis>: a charset
          to be used whenever possible, for example when creating pages or
          when serving files that do not specify a charset. It is <emphasis
          role="bold">highly recommended</emphasis> that you keep the default,
          that matches the encoding used by the underlying platform.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="modules">
    <title>Modules</title>

    <section id="standard_modules">
      <title>Standard Modules</title>

      <para>A web page is not just a block of text. Many pages on the web
      perform some common tasks: image galleries, mail forms, news and so on.
      While one can just write down those pages each time, it is clear that
      some automation is possible in those cases. The MeshCMS answer to this
      demand is the concept of <firstterm>module</firstterm>. A module is a
      configurable zone in a page: when you edit the page, you have some boxes
      where you can select a module and provide an
      <firstterm>argument</firstterm> (usually a file or directory) and some
      advanced parameters. If the argument is not specified, modules behave
      differently: some can default to the folder that contains the page,
      while others will do nothing.<note>
          <para>the argument of a module is not necessarily a directory or a
          file. For example, in the mail module you can specify an e-mail
          address as argument, and a standard form will be created using that
          address as recipient.</para>
        </note></para>

      <para>When you edit a page, you will have the chance to configure as
      many modules as the page theme specifies. Normally all themes should
      contain a module at least.</para>

      <para>MeshCMS provides some modules, and others can be created by
      everyone that is able to write a JSP page. Here's a table of standard
      modules:</para>

      <table>
        <title>MeshCMS Standard Module Templates</title>

        <tgroup cols="4">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Module Template</entry>

              <entry>Purpose</entry>

              <entry>Action</entry>

              <entry>Behavior Without Argument</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>chat</entry>

              <entry>Creation of a simple chat</entry>

              <entry>Provides a form to chat with other people looking at the
              same page</entry>

              <entry>Argument is always ignored</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><classname>downloads</classname></entry>

              <entry>Creation of a list of downloads</entry>

              <entry>Provides a link for each file in the argument</entry>

              <entry>Does nothing</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><classname>gallery</classname></entry>

              <entry>Creation of an image gallery</entry>

              <entry>Shows a thumbnail with a link for each image file in the
              argument</entry>

              <entry>Uses the folder that contains the page</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>headlines</entry>

              <entry>inclusion of other pages, showing the first words
              only</entry>

              <entry>Shows the first words of each page, followed by a link to
              the full page</entry>

              <entry>Does nothing</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><classname>include</classname></entry>

              <entry>Inclusion of files in the page</entry>

              <entry>Shows the title and body of each page file in the
              argument</entry>

              <entry>Does nothing</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><classname>include_as_text</classname></entry>

              <entry>Inclusion of files in the page</entry>

              <entry>Includes each file as plain text</entry>

              <entry>Does nothing</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><classname>list_pages</classname></entry>

              <entry>Creation of a list of links</entry>

              <entry>Shows a link for each page file in the argument</entry>

              <entry>Uses the folder that contains the page</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><classname>mail</classname></entry>

              <entry>Creation of a mail form</entry>

              <entry>Shows a mail form according to the information contained
              in the argument, which must be a file used as form
              descriptor</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>Please always specify a form descriptor or an
              e-mail address</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><classname>parse</classname></entry>

              <entry>Inclusion of dynamic files</entry>

              <entry>Includes all files in the argument using the
              pageContext.include() method. This module template is intended
              for advanced users</entry>

              <entry>Does nothing</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><classname>site_map</classname></entry>

              <entry>Creation of a site map</entry>

              <entry>Creates a site map starting from the argument
              path</entry>

              <entry>Starts from the folder that contains the page</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <section id="module_chat">
        <title>Chat</title>

        <para>The chat module has been created by Pierre Mtras and provides a
        simple, AJAX-based chat. To use it, simply select the module: no
        argument is needed.</para>

        <para>Advanced parameters:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><parameter>css</parameter>: the name of a css class.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Downloads</title>

        <para>The downloads module creates a list of downloadable files. An
        icon and the size are shown near the name of each file.</para>

        <para>Advanced parameters:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><parameter>css</parameter>: the name of a css class;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><parameter>date</parameter>: the type of file date to be
            shown. Possible values are <option>none</option> (default),
            <option>normal</option> (date only) and <option>full</option>
            (date and time).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Gallery</title>

        <para>The gallery module creates thumbnails for a list of images.
        Thumbnails link to full images, and file names are used as
        captions.</para>

        <para>Advanced parameters:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><parameter>css</parameter>: the name of a css class;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><parameter>captions</parameter>: defines if the captions
            must be shown or not. Values are <option>true</option> (default)
            and <option>false</option>;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><parameter>columns</parameter>: defines the number of
            columns (default <option>3</option>);</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><parameter>quality</parameter>: defines the algorithm used
            to create the thumbnails. Values are <option>low</option>
            (default) and <option>high</option>. High quality requires more
            CPU and RAM (thumbnails are cached anyway).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="tag_library">
    <title>Tag Library</title>

    <para>MeshCMS provides a library of custom tags to ease the creation of
    themes. Some are mandatory, others can be useful in many situations. The
    following sections explain each tag separately. As an example, the
    <code>&lt;cms:tagname&gt;</code> form is used, which implies the following
    declaration at the beginning of the theme file:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;%@ taglib uri="meshcms-taglib" prefix="cms" %&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Mandatory tags are: <link
    linkend="tag_editor">&lt;cms:editor&gt;</link>, <link
    linkend="tag_pagehead">&lt;cms:pagehead&gt;</link> and <link
    linkend="tag_pagebody">&lt;cms:pagebody&gt;</link>.</para>

    <section id="tag_editor">
      <title>&lt;cms:editor&gt;</title>

      <para>This tag is <emphasis>mandatory</emphasis> and must enclose all
      tags of type <code>&lt;cms:pagebody&gt;</code>,
      <code>&lt;cms:module&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;cms:mailform&gt;</code> in
      the theme file. Since these three tags are always used inside the HTML
      <code>&lt;body&gt;</code> tag, usually the
      <code>&lt;cms:editor&gt;</code> is inserted immediately after the
      <code>&lt;body&gt;</code>:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;html&gt;
...
&lt;body&gt;&lt;cms:editor&gt;
... body content...
&lt;/cms:editor&gt;&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The purpose of this tag is to insert a <code>&lt;form&gt;</code>
      element when the page is being edited. For that reason, you must also
      enclose any other <code>&lt;form&gt;</code> tag into a
      <code>&lt;cms:ifnotediting&gt;</code> tag, so your forms won't be shown
      during page editing (HTML does not allow nested forms).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_pagehead">
      <title>&lt;cms:pagehead&gt;</title>

      <para>Inserts some headers found in the page. This tag is
      <emphasis>mandatory</emphasis> since it is needed when editing pages.
      This tag has no attributes.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_pagebody">
      <title>&lt;cms:pagebody&gt;</title>

      <para>Inserts the body of the page. This tag is
      <emphasis>mandatory</emphasis> since it is needed when editing pages (it
      makes no sense to have a theme that does not show the contents of the
      page anyway). This tag has no attributes.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_pagetitle">
      <title>&lt;cms:pagetitle&gt;</title>

      <para>This tag prints the title of the page. It has one
      attribute:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>default</parameter>: default title to be used when
          the page has no title. This attribute is optional and its default
          value is <code>&amp;nbsp;</code>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <example>
        <title>A simple title</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;title&gt;My Site: &lt;cms:pagetitle /&gt;&lt;/title&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>

      <note>
        <para>the use of <code>&lt;cms:pagetitle&gt;</code> is not limited to
        the HTML <code>&lt;title&gt;</code> tag: you can use it elsewhere to
        repeat the title of the page, and you can use anything else within the
        HTML <code>&lt;title&gt;</code> tag.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_breadcrumbs">
      <title>&lt;cms:breadcrumbs&gt;</title>

      <para>Creates a list of titles/links for all the pages from the site
      root (included) to the current page (can be excluded).
      Attributes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>separator</parameter>: the text between elements
          (default is a space);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>mode</parameter>: the type of breadcrumbs. Possible
          values are <option>titles</option> (default) and
          <option>links</option>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>style</parameter>: a css style for links (default
          is no style);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>target</parameter>: the target for links (default
          is no target, hence same window);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>current</parameter>: boolean value to
          include/exclude the current page (default is
          <option>true</option>);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>pre</parameter>: a text to be added before the
          first element. It won't be added if there are no elements at
          all;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>post</parameter>: a text to be added after the last
          element. It won't be added if there are no elements at all.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <example>
        <title>The most common breadcrumbs</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:breadcrumbs mode="links" pre="You are viewing: " separator=" &amp;raquo; " /&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_defaultcss">
      <title>&lt;cms:defaultcss&gt;</title>

      <para>Creates a link to the default style sheets for that page and for
      the additional. You can use it (recommended) or import/link styles as
      usual. This tag has no attributes.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_contextpath">
      <title>&lt;cms:contextpath&gt;</title>

      <para>Inserts the context path, i.e. the value of
      <code>HttpServletRequest.getContextPath()</code>. Useful for absolute
      paths, since the context path might be added when the web application
      context is not root in its host. This tag has no attributes.</para>

      <example>
        <title>An absolute link</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;a href="&lt;cms:contextpath /&gt;/dir/page.html"&gt;An absolute link&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_themepath">
      <title>&lt;cms:themepath&gt;</title>

      <para>Inserts the complete path of the folder that contains the current
      theme. Very useful to insert files of the theme itself. This tag has no
      attributes.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Insert an image located in the theme folder</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;img src="&lt;cms:themepath /&gt;/logo.jpg"&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_adminmenu">
      <title>&lt;cms:adminmenu&gt;</title>

      <para>This tag inserts a menu to access some specific MeshCMS functions
      when the user has logged in:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Control Panel</emphasis>: a link to the
          Control Panel;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Edit this page</emphasis>: a link to
          edit the current page visually;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Edit source</emphasis>: a link to edit
          the source of the current page;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">New page</emphasis>: a link to create a
          new page at the same level of the current one;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">New child page</emphasis>: a link to
          create a new child page.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Some links won't appear if they are not appropriate. If no user
      has logged in, the behavior depends on the mode attribute. You should
      always use this tag in a theme, since it offers the most comfortable way
      to edit pages.</para>

      <para>Attributes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>mode</parameter>: what to display before a user has
          logged in. There are 2 possible values: <option>normal</option>
          (default) displays a link to the login page and
          <option>hidden</option> shows nothing.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>separator</parameter>: the text between elements
          (default is a space);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>style</parameter>: a css style for links (default
          is no style).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <example>
        <title>A vertical admin menu</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:adminmenu separator="&lt;br /&gt;" /&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_simplemenu">
      <title>&lt;cms:simplemenu&gt;</title>

      <para>Creates a simple textual menu, similar to a typical CMS menu
      (first level + path to current level + current level).</para>

      <para>Attributes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>path</parameter>: the path used as root for the
          menu. Default is the root of the site;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>space</parameter>: the number of pixels used to
          indent the menu. Default is <option>8</option>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>bullet</parameter>: the HTML code used as bullet in
          the menu. Default is <option>&amp;middot;</option>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>style</parameter>: a css style for menu elements
          (default is no style);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>expand</parameter>: set <option>this</option> to
          true to expand the intermediate levels of the menu (by default it is
          <option>false</option> and only expands the first and last
          levels).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_tigramenu">
      <title>&lt;cms:tigramenu&gt;</title>

      <para>Creates a JavaScript menu (using <ulink
      url="http://www.softcomplex.com/products/tigra_menu/">this free
      script</ulink>). This script needs to insert some code in the head tag
      and some in the body tag, so you must call this tag twice in the same
      page.</para>

      <para>Attributes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>part</parameter>: the part of code. Possible values
          are <option>head</option> and <option>body</option>. You must use
          both values (the former within the head tag, the latter within the
          body tag);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>path</parameter>: the path used as root for the
          menu. Default is the root of the site. Use this attribute when
          <parameter>part</parameter> has the <option>head</option>
          value;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>placeholder</parameter>: a boolean value to include
          a transparent image with the size of the menu. This is useful when
          the layout of the page does not use absolute positioning as the
          script does. Default is <option>false</option>. Use this attribute
          olny when <parameter>part</parameter> has the <option>body</option>
          value.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If you use this tag in a theme, you must include the files
      <filename>menu.js</filename>, <filename>menu_tpl.js</filename> and
      <filename>menu.css</filename> in the same folder of the
      <filename>main.jsp</filename> theme file.
      <filename>menu_tpl.js</filename> and <filename>menu.css</filename> can
      be customized to get the desired result, as videly illustrated in the
      documentation of the script.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_links">
      <title>&lt;cms:links&gt;</title>

      <para>Creates a list of links to pages in the same level (i.e.
      folder).</para>

      <para>Attributes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>separator</parameter>: the text between elements
          (default is a space);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>style</parameter>: a css style for links (default
          is no style);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>target</parameter>: the target for links (default
          is no target, hence same window);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>current</parameter>: boolean value to
          include/exclude the current page (default is
          <option>true</option>);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>pre</parameter>: a text to be added before the
          first element. It won't be added if there are no elements at
          all;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>post</parameter>: a text to be added after the last
          element. It won't be added if there are no elements at all.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_module">
      <title>&lt;cms:module&gt;</title>

      <para>This tag allows to include a <link linkend="modules">module</link>
      in the place where it is located in the page.</para>

      <para>Attributes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>name</parameter>: the description of the module
          content, in the form <option>template:argument</option>. The
          template can be omitted: in this case the colon can be omitted too,
          and the Include template will be used. The fact that this attribute
          is called name can be misleading: it is a heritage of a previous
          version;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>date</parameter>: the format of the date. This is
          passed to the include template and might be used or not (for example
          <classname>Include</classname> uses it). Possible values are
          <option>none</option> (default), <option>normal</option> and
          <option>full</option>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>style</parameter>: a css style. This is passed to
          the include template and might be used or not (for example
          <classname>Include</classname> uses it). Default is no style;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>location</parameter> (required): the name of the
          module location. <emphasis>All modules in a theme must have
          different location names</emphasis>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>alt</parameter>: a string that is inserted when the
          module is not used (default <option>&amp;nbsp;</option>).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <example>
        <title>A fixed module that includes some files located in the
        <filename>/include/news</filename> folder</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:module location="news" name="includes/news" date="normal" style="news" /&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>

      <example>
        <title>A module that can be configured while editing the page</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:module location="afterbody" /&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>

      <example>
        <title>A module that shows a site map starting from the folder of the
        page, using <code>(none)</code> to pass an empty argument:</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:module location="sitemap" name="site_map:(none)" /&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>A note about locations: suppose to edit some pages using a theme
      that contains two configurable modules, whose locations are left and
      afterbody. Modules will be saved in the page with those location names.
      If you change theme, those modules will appear if the new theme contains
      configurable modules with the same location names. So it suggested to
      use common names for module locations. This is a possible
      convention:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>left</option> for a module in the left column;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>right</option> for a module in the right
          column;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>top</option> for a module at the top of the
          page;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>afterbody</option> for a module after the page
          body;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>bottom</option> for a module at the bottom of the
          page;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>numbers for modules below others (<option>left2</option>,
          <option>right2</option>, etc.)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Usually a theme will contain 1, 2 or 3 modules, but there's no
      limit to their number.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_mailform">
      <title>&lt;cms:mailform&gt;</title>

      <para>Creates a standard form to send e-mail messages. This can be used
      to receive a feedback from visitors. The form will only appear in pages
      that have a recipient specified (it can be set when editing the page).
      This tag has no attributes.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_lastmodified">
      <title>&lt;cms:lastmodified&gt;</title>

      <para>Writes the date of the last modification of the current
      file.</para>

      <para>Attributes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>date</parameter>: the format of the date. Possible
          values are <option>normal</option> (default) and
          <option>full</option>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>mode</parameter>: since usually it makes no sense
          to use this tag for server-side pages (e.g. JSPs), you can set this
          attribute to <option>static</option> (default) to show the date for
          static files only, or you can use <option>all</option> to always
          show it;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>pre</parameter>: a text to be added before the
          date. It won't be added if the date is not shown;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>post</parameter>: a text to be added after the
          date. It won't be added if the date is not shown.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Please note that the last modification date refers to the file of
      the page and does not reflects the dates of other files included through
      modules.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_user">
      <title>&lt;cms:user&gt;</title>

      <para>This tag shows some info about the current user.</para>

      <para>Attributes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>id</parameter>: indicates which user information
          must be shown. Value can be <option>username</option>,
          <option>e-mail</option> (or <option>email</option>), or another user
          detail (<option>salutation</option>, <option>name</option>,
          <option>surname</option>, <option>company</option>,
          <option>address</option>, <option>zip</option>,
          <option>city</option>, <option>state</option>,
          <option>country</option>, <option>phone_number</option>,
          <option>fax_number</option>, <option>mobile_phone_number</option>).
          If id is not specified, the value displayed depends on what
          information is available.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <example>
        <title>Welcoming a user when he has logged in</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:ifuser&gt;Welcome &lt;cms:user /&gt;!&lt;/cms:ifuser&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_ifuser">
      <title>&lt;cms:ifuser&gt;, &lt;cms:ifnotuser&gt;</title>

      <para>These tags mark a part of the page that must be shown only when a
      user has logged in or not.</para>

      <para>These tags have no attributes.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Displaying a message to a user</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:ifuser&gt;Welcome &lt;cms:user /&gt;!&lt;/cms:ifuser&gt;
&lt;cms:ifnotuser&gt;You are not logged in&lt;/cms:ifnotuser&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_ifediting">
      <title>&lt;cms:ifediting&gt;, &lt;cms:ifnotediting&gt;</title>

      <para>These tags are used to mark a part of the page that must be shown
      only when editing or viewing a page.</para>

      <para>These tags have no attributes.</para>

      <para>The <code>&lt;cms:ifnotediting&gt;</code> tag is mainly used to
      enclose forms that would otherwise conflict with the main editing
      form.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Inserting a search form without conflicting with the MeshCMS
        editor</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:ifnotediting&gt;
 &lt;!-- Search Google --&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
   &lt;FORM method=GET action="http://www.google.com/search"&gt;
    &lt;input type=hidden name=ie value=UTF-8&gt;
    &lt;input type=hidden name=oe value=UTF-8&gt;
    &lt;TABLE bgcolor="#FFFFFF"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
     &lt;A HREF="http://www.google.com/"&gt;
     &lt;IMG SRC="http://www.google.com/logos/Logo_40wht.gif" 
      border="0" ALT="Google" align="absmiddle"&gt;&lt;/A&gt;
     &lt;INPUT TYPE=text name=q size=25 maxlength=255 value=""&gt;
     &lt;INPUT type=submit name=btnG VALUE="Google Search"&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/TABLE&gt;
   &lt;/FORM&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
 &lt;!-- Search Google --&gt;
&lt;/cms:ifnotediting&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_ifmodule">
      <title>&lt;cms:ifmodule&gt;, &lt;cms:ifnotmodule&gt;</title>

      <para>These tags are used to display a part of the page only when the
      specified module is active or not.</para>

      <para>Attributes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>location</parameter> (required): the name of the
          module location.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <example>
        <title>Adding some HTML around a module</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:ifmodule location="afterbody"&gt;
 &lt;div align="center"&gt;Module title&lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;cms:module location="afterbody" /&gt;
 &lt;div align="center"&gt;End of module&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/cms:ifmodule&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section id="tag_ifmailform">
      <title>&lt;cms:ifmailform&gt;, &lt;cms:ifnotmailform&gt;</title>

      <para>These tags are used to display a part of the page only if a
      recipient has been specified to receive messages from that page.</para>

      <para>These tags have no attributes:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Adding some HTML around a mail form</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;cms:ifmailform&gt;
 &lt;div align="center"&gt;Send a message&lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;cms:mailform /&gt;
&lt;/cms:ifmailform&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>